<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[PRT Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://newfolder.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://newfolder.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-23T13:15:27-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://newfolder.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kenneth Morton and Peter Torrione]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hi]]></title>
    <link href="http://newfolder.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/hi/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-23T13:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://newfolder.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/hi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi,</p>

<p>Thanks for checking out the PRT. The PRT is intended to help people who do machine learning handle the most common classification tasks within MATLAB.  This includes things like cross-validation, data visualization, classifier development and feature selection. The PRT includes object types for data set storage, pre-processing, classification, clustering, distance calculations, outlier removal, kernel learning, data generation, scoring and classifier evaluation, feature selection, random variable definitions, and visualization. We think it serves as a great platform for both machine learning research and applied algorithm development (that&rsquo;s why we built it!).</p>

<p>The PRT is free and released under the MIT license which means that it is free for academic and commercial use. The PRT is hosted on <a href="https://github.com/newfolder/PRT">GitHub</a> so feel free to fork or clone the repository or just download the latest <a href="https://github.com/newfolder/PRT/zipball/master">zip</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="../prtdoc/prtDocInstallation.html">installation instructions</a> to get you up and running. Once installed, open up MATLAB&reg;, and follow through with our <a href="../prtdoc/prtDocGettingStarted.html">Getting Started</a> guide, which will walk you through some examples of using the PRT in practice and show you what the PRT can do.</p>

<p>Even though there are a lot of M-files in the PRT, we’ve built the PRT to be easy to use and to make it easy to find what you need from within MATLAB.  For example, to find a list of all classifiers in the PRT, simply type “prtClass” and then <tab> at the MATLAB command prompt.  Other object types behave the same way, e.g., prtPreProc <tab>. If you have any feed back or questions don&rsquo;t hesitate to ask in our <a href="../forum">forums</a>, on <a href="https://github.com/newfolder/PRT">GitHub</a> or through email at <a href="mailto:prt@newfolderconsulting.com"><a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#112;&#114;&#x74;&#64;&#110;&#x65;&#x77;&#102;&#x6f;&#x6c;&#x64;&#101;&#x72;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#115;&#117;&#x6c;&#116;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x70;&#114;&#116;&#64;&#110;&#101;&#119;&#102;&#111;&#x6c;&#100;&#x65;&#114;&#x63;&#111;&#110;&#115;&#117;&#108;&#x74;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#109;</a></a>.</p>

<p>We are going to start blogging every once in a while about the PRT and things it can do. We hope that it starts a conversation about the types of things people are doing with the PRT and what things people might want the PRT to do in the future.</p>

<p>Talk to you soon.  Happy coding!</p>

<p>-Kenny and Pete</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://newfolder.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-23T12:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://newfolder.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is new home of the PRT blog. In time all of the previous posts will be imported. Bare with us.</p>

<p>~Kenny</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
